动物王朝
Lions are the very image of majesty.
狮子是庄严的代名词
And, indeed, of Africa itself.
也是非洲的代名词
Their strength lies in the power of the pride,
它们的强大 来自于狮群的力量
their tight-knit family.
紧密相连的家族的力量
Lions have ruled the savannahs for millennia.
数千年来 狮子一直统治着热带大草原
And yet, within the last 20 years or so,
然而 在最近20多年中
their numbers have fallen by almost half.
它们的数量减少了将近一半
Our team has spent two years following perhaps the most famous
我们小组花费两年时间 跟踪可能是全世界最著名的
lion family of all, the Marsh pride of Kenya's Masai Mara.
狮子家族 肯尼亚马赛马拉的玛莎狮群
As we join them, the very survival of this great dynasty
在我们开始观察它们的时候 这个伟大王朝的生存
is under threat.
正面临威胁
Their future depends entirely on the strength and determination
它们的未来完全取决于一位卓越领导者的
of one extraordinary leader.
力量与意志
Perhaps the most powerful in the history of the Marsh pride.
或许它是玛莎狮群历史上最强大的领导者
A lioness known as Charm.
一头叫做查姆的雌狮
狮子
The Masai Mara.
这里是马赛马拉
The pride have always thrived here through an alliance
狮群一直在此生生不息
between powerful alpha males to protect the family
强势的雄狮结成联盟 保护家族
and experienced females to raise the cubs.
并且与雌狮一起抚养幼崽
But, for the first time in the pride's history,
然而在狮群的历史上
this alliance has been shattered.
这个联盟第一次分崩离析
The family has been abandoned by all the adult males.
所有成年雄狮都抛弃了家族
The survival of the pride now rests upon the shoulders of Charm
如今狮群生存的重担落到了查姆
and her cousin, Sienna.
以及它的表亲西耶娜肩上
The only remaining adults.
它们是仅存的成年狮子
If their young are to reach adulthood and the dynasty return
要想让幼崽长大成年 王朝恢复昔日的辉煌
to full strength, they must now both protect and feed the whole family.
它们必须保护并且养活整个家族
August.
8月
Following the recent rains, it's a time of plenty.
近日降雨之后 丰衣足食的时间到了
The lions are surrounded by wildebeest
狮子的周围全是
on their annual migration.
开始年度迁徙的角马
A quarter-tonne bull would make a good meal
一头重达250公斤的公牛
for all ten of the pride.
可以让狮群的十头狮子饱餐一顿
But even though Charm is an experienced hunter,
尽管查姆的狩猎经验十分丰富
most attempts end in failure.
大多数尝试却以失败告终
Charm uses her hind legs to knock the wildebeest off-balance.
查姆用后腿打破角马的平衡
The smallest cubs won't be able to catch food for themselves
最小的幼崽要等到12个月后
for another 12 months.
才能独自捕食
Their ever-growing appetites mean that Charm and Sienna
它们日益增大的胃口意味着查姆与西耶娜
have to hunt around the clock.
必须连续不断地狩猎
The females are often forced to head out alone.
雌狮常常被迫独自外出
Tonight, it's Sienna's turn.
今晚 轮到西耶娜了
Sunrise.
太阳升起
Sienna is seriously injured.
西耶娜受了重伤
She's too week to move.
它太虚弱了 无法移动
A lone lion is always at risk of attack by buffalo,
落单的狮子往往面临被攻击的风险
hyenas, even other lion prides.
野牛 鬣狗 甚至其他狮群都可能对它虎视眈眈
It's evening, and Sienna hasn't returned to her family.
入夜 万籁俱寂 西耶娜还没回来
Now, everything depends on Charm.
如今一切担子都落到了查姆的肩上
As night falls, Charm has no choice but to head out to hunt,
随着夜幕降临 查姆别无选择 只能外出狩猎
leaving the vulnerable cubs alone.
留下容易受到伤害的幼崽
She's being trailed.
它被跟踪了
Hyenas.
鬣狗
They'll attack lone lions if they get the chance,
一有机会 它们就会攻击落单的狮子
to steal any kill they make.
偷走它们的猎物
Charm must work fast before they find her.
查姆必须抢在被它们发现之前 速战速决
They've tracked her down.
它们找到它了
On her own, she couldn't hold them off.
单枪匹马的它难以驱赶这群不速之客
But another of the pride has been following Charm.
然而狮群的另一个成员一直尾随查姆
Her three-year-old daughter, Yaya.
它三岁的女儿雅雅
The rest of the pride arrive.
狮群的其他成员赶到了
To eat.
大快朵颐
Yaya has stepped up to help defend the pride and feed her family.
雅雅走上前 帮助保护狮群 喂养家族
Daughters stay with their mothers for life, and may eventually
女儿与母亲终生相伴 或许
have cubs of their own.
最终还会产下自己的幼崽
Yaya is not yet an adult, but as Charm's eldest daughter,
雅雅还未成年 但是身为查姆最大的女儿
she's next in line to lead the pride.
它是狮群下一任的领导者
Charm also has a three-year-old son, Tatu.
查姆还有一个三岁的儿子 塔图
The beginnings of an impressive mane are a sign
开始长出威严的鬃毛
of his approaching adulthood.
是他接近成年的信号
Like every adolescent, Tatu can't resist the chance
和所有青春期的狮子一样 测试日益增强的力量的机会摆在面前
to test his growing strength.
塔图难以抵抗
Even against a two-tonne hippo.
哪怕对方是两吨重的河马
But he's not the only young male in this pride.
不过在这个狮群里 它不是唯一的年轻雄狮
His cousin, Red.
这是它的表弟瑞德
Over the last few months, the two of them have begun
在过去几个月内 它俩开始
to forge an alliance.
结成联盟
But even together, they're not really going to worry
可是就算联手 一头愤怒的河马
an angry hippo.
也没有把它们放在眼里
Unlike their sisters, sons always leave their family
和姐妹们不同 雄狮在成年后
when they reach adulthood.
通常会离开家族
Their growing bond may enable them to leave as a powerful partnership.
越来越亲密的关系 让它们在离开后组成了强大的搭档
Eventually, they'll fight other males to try and take over a pride
最终它们将与其他雄狮搏斗
of their own.
试图掌管自己的狮群
But for the time being, they still need Charm
不过暂时 它们依然需要
to look after them.
查姆的照顾
It's been four days since Sienna was attacked.
距离西耶娜被攻击已经过去四天了
She's back on her feet.
它虽然再次站了起来
But she's in urgent need of a meal.
却急需填饱肚子
She simply doesn't have the strength.
它已经没有足够的力气
As they mature, young males begin to explore the boundaries
发育成熟后 年轻的雄狮开始探索
of the pride's territory.
狮群领地的边界
Red has ventured out alone.
瑞德独自冒险外出
And blundered straight into the middle of the hyena clan.
径直闯进了一群鬣狗中间
He's trapped by over 20 of them.
它被20多只鬣狗包围了
The pack tries to wear him down.
鬣狗试图拖垮它
This number of hyenas could kill him.
这么多的鬣狗可以置它于死地
It's impossible to fight them all at once.
它寡不敌众
He can't keep them at bay for much longer.
它再也阻止不了它们的进攻
He's tiring fast.
它的体力快速减退
His ally, Tatu, has heard the commotion.
它的盟友塔图听到了骚乱的声音
Now, the odds have changed.
这下局势改变了
Even for 20 hyenas, a pair of male lions
哪怕对20只鬣狗来说 两头雄狮也太过强大
is too much to take on.
无法拿下
Red is lucky.
瑞德是幸运的
Tatu has saved his cousin's life.
塔图救了表弟一命
After weeks of feeding on scraps, Sienna has grown strong enough
在吃了几周的零星食物之后 西耶娜恢复了足够的体力
to try and rejoin her family.
能够返回家族
She greets Charm first.
它首先和查姆打招呼
Even after being apart for so long, the bond between them
即使分离已久 它们之间的感情
is still strong.
依然深厚
Yaya also welcomes Sienna back into the pride.
雅雅也欢迎西耶娜重返狮群
At last, Charm's family are back together.
查姆的家族最终团聚了
Charm not only has her hunting partner back,
对查姆来说 不仅一个狩猎搭档回归
but another hunter is emerging.
另一个猎手正浮出水面
Yaya is becoming a powerful lioness.
雅雅逐渐长成一头强大的雌狮
She's learned how to stalk.
它学会了如何跟踪猎物
Stay low.
低调
Approach silently.
悄声靠近
And from downwind.
循着顺风的方向
But the key to a successful ambush is not being noticed.
不过成功伏击的关键在于不被察觉
Now it's seen her, the wildebeest, with its sharp horns,
这下角马看见它了 角马凭借锋利的角
has the advantage.
占据上风
But Yaya is learning.
不过雅雅正在学习
Mother and daughter are starting to develop their partnership.
母亲和女儿开始培养合作关系
It's October.
10月到了
The great wildebeest migration never stops.
角马大迁徙永不停歇
And now, they're leaving the Masai Mara.
它们正离开马赛马拉
For Charm and her family, food is about to become
对查姆和家族来说 觅食的难度
much more difficult to find.
即将大大增加
The plains are now empty.
如今的平原空空荡荡
And, in search of food,
为了寻找食物
Charm leads the pride to the edge of their range.
查姆带领狮群去往它们活动范围的边缘
Here, she finds another kind of prey.
它在这里发现了另一种猎物
Cattle, illegally brought into the lions' territory to graze.
牛群 被非法赶到狮子领地吃草
An opportunity to feed her hungry family.
喂饱饥肠辘辘的家族的好机会
But hunting cattle can lead to disaster.
然而狩猎牛群可能导致灾难
To protect their livestock,
为了保护牲畜
herdsmen sometimes put out poisoned bait.
放牧者有时候会放出有毒的诱饵
Lions can't tell when a meal is toxic.
狮子分辨不出有毒的食物
A week later, Charm's one-year-old son is so ill he can hardly stand.
一周后 查姆一岁的儿子病入膏肓 几乎无法站立
The whole pride are showing the signs of poisoning.
整个狮群都出现了中毒的迹象
And Sienna is missing once again.
西耶娜再次失踪了
As the temperature climbs, the pride heads off to find shade.
随着气温升高 狮群出发寻找阴凉
But the struggling cub is too weak to follow.
可是这头挣扎的幼崽太虚弱 无法跟随大部队
Charm needs to stay with the rest of the pride.
查姆必须与狮群剩下的成员待在一起
Hours later, the cub still hasn't caught up with his mother.
数小时后 幼崽依然赶不上它的母亲
And there's no sign of Sienna, either.
也没有西耶娜的踪影
The next day, Charm returns to her son's side.
第二天 查姆回到儿子身边
He's still very unsteady.
它的情况依旧很不稳定
But his mother can't abandon the rest of the pride.
但是母亲不能抛下剩下的狮群成员
For the sake of the pride, Charm abandons her young cub.
为了狮群 查姆抛下了年幼的儿子
The others are waiting for her.
其他狮子等待着它
They need her now more than ever.
此时的它们比任何时候都更需要它
She will never see her son, or Sienna, alive again.
它再也看不到自己的儿子 还有西耶娜活着了
Despite her losses, there may still be a future
尽管尝到了失去的痛苦
for Charm and her dynasty.
查姆和它的王朝或许还有未来
Her eldest cubs, Yaya and Tatu, have survived the poisoning.
它年纪最大的幼崽 雅雅和塔图挺过了中毒的难关
Charm keeps the pride moving in a constant search for prey.
查姆带领狮群前行 不断寻找猎物
Catching enough food is hard, even with Yaya's help.
哪怕在雅雅的帮助下 捕捉足够的食物也并非易事
But Charm is relentless.
然而查姆毫不松懈
The younger members of the pride try to follow her example.
更年轻的狮群成员以它为榜样
Even with little to hunt and the constant harassment
尽管可以狩猎的对象少之又少 加上鬣狗的
of hyenas, Charm's skill and experience as a leader
不断骚扰 查姆身为领导者的能力与经验
is keeping the pride alive.
依然保持狮群活下去
A few weeks later, her efforts begin to be rewarded.
几周后 它的努力得到了回报
Tatu and Red are now over four years old,
如今塔图和瑞德四岁多了
ready to take the final step to adulthood.
准备迈出最后一步 跨入成年的大门
It's time for them to leave the pride.
到了它们离开狮群的时候了
For Charm, this is success.
对查姆而言 这是成功
They head out as a partnership, to battle other males,
成为搭档的它们渐行渐远 去和其他雄狮争斗
to win a pride of their own,
赢得自己的狮群
and continue the family's bloodline elsewhere.
在别处延续家族的血统
But Charm still needs to get the remaining four female cubs
但是查姆依然需要抚养剩下的四头年幼雌狮
safely to adulthood.
直至它们平安长大
One early morning in May...
5月的一个清晨
..the roar of adult male lions.
成年雄狮在吼叫
Two new males, outsiders, are searching for a pride
两头新出现的雄狮 外来者 正在寻找狮群
to take over as their own.
试图将其占为己有
New males could bring the possibility
新雄狮可以带来
of a new generation of cubs.
新一代幼崽的可能性
But they could just as easily bring disaster.
但是它们也可以轻易地带来灾难
Soon, the new males begin to impose their authority
很快 新雄狮开始对玛莎狮群
on the Marsh pride.
施加权威
Charm's youngest daughter is still too young to breed.
查姆最小的女儿还太年轻 无法繁殖
To the males, she's nothing more than another mouth
在雄狮眼里 它不过是需要分享食物的
to share food with.
另一张嘴
They don't want her in their pride.
它们不希望它加入自己的狮群
Try as she might, Charm struggles to defend her daughter.
查姆竭尽全力 挣扎着保护女儿
Even she is no match for an adult male.
哪怕它并不是一头成年雄狮的对手
Charm tries distracting them,
查姆横亘在它们与幼崽之间
putting herself between them and her cub.
试图引开雄狮的注意
But it's no good.
可是没用
If her daughter stays, the males will eventually kill her.
如果它的女儿留在原地 雄狮最终会要了它的命
The cub has no choice but to leave.
幼崽别无选择 只能离开
And the males don't stop there.
雄狮并未就此停止
Every young cub is driven out.
幼崽统统被赶走
Their future is uncertain.
它们的未来是个未知数
There's nothing Charm can do.
查姆无能为力
Eight months ago, Charm's pride numbered ten lions.
八个月后 查姆的狮群达到了十头狮子
Of them, only she and Yaya now remain.
其中留下来的只有它和雅雅
The return of the wildebeest signals the end, at last,
角马的回归 宣告着艰难的时光
of the hard times.
终于结束了
Time for a new beginning.
新的帷幕拉开了
Charm is starting the process of rebuilding the Marsh pride.
查姆开始着手重建玛莎狮群的大业
She and one of the males have separated themselves
它和一头雄狮远离其他成员
from the rest of the group.
享受二人世界
Females are only able to conceive once every few months.
每隔几个月 雌狮才能怀孕一次
For those crucial days, the male won't leave her side.
在那些关键的日子里 雄狮守在它身边
Charm stays close to him to strengthen their bond.
查姆对它寸步不离 增进感情
If the male isn't certain any future cubs are his,
如果雄狮不确定幼崽是否是自己的
he will probably kill them.
它可能会下杀手
Four months later.
四个月后
Charm is alone, away from the pride.
查姆形单影只 远离狮群
Over the last 14 months, her dynasty has faced ruin.
在过去的14个月中 它的王朝面临毁灭
But now, there is new hope.
可是如今 出现了新的希望
Just two weeks old.
这只才两周大
Charm gave birth away from the others.
查姆离开狮群 生下幼崽
Inquisitive and clumsy lions could be a threat to the newborns.
好奇而笨拙的狮子 可能对新生儿构成威胁
But her two cubs are still extremely vulnerable.
不过它的两头幼崽依然相当娇弱
Buffaloes seek out lion cubs and will kill them
野牛四处寻找幼狮 一有机会
if they get the chance.
就会杀了它们
She shields them with her body.
它用身体挡住它们
Without her to protect them, the buffalo will trample
没有它的保护 野牛会把幼崽
them to death.
踩死
Charm has forced the entire herd to back down.
查姆逼迫整个牛群撤退
Life is always dangerous for lion cubs.
对幼狮来说 生活充满了危险
But these two have an experienced mother to look after them.
不过这两个小家伙的妈妈经验丰富 能够照顾它们
At last, Charm's pride is increasing again.
最终 查姆的狮群再次扩大
One male and one female.
新添了一头雄狮和一头雌狮
And these cubs may soon be joined by more.
很快会有更多的幼崽加入
Yaya has paired off with the other adult male.
雅雅与另一头成年雄狮结伴离开了
Soon, she too will have cubs.
它很快也将诞下幼崽
Charm's grandchildren.
查姆的外孙
Charm is taking her cubs to meet the rest of the Marsh pride
查姆带着幼崽 与玛莎狮群的其他成员
for the first time.
第一次会合
Once their father has accepted the cubs, he'll defend them
一旦幼崽的父亲接受了它们 它就会和它们的母亲一样
as fiercely as their mother.
拼命地保护它们
They are the future of his dynasty, too.
它们也是它的王朝的未来
Charm has been away from the pride since giving birth,
自从产子以来 查姆一直远离狮群
and hasn't seen Yaya for weeks.
数周没有见过雅雅
Their bond has held through perhaps the hardest times
在狮群历史上最艰难的日子里
in the pride's history.
它们情比金坚
With her daughter pregnant and her son looking for a pride
女儿怀孕 儿子寻找自己的狮群
of his own, Charm's dynasty and the Marsh pride will live on.
查姆的王朝 玛莎狮群得以延续
This extraordinary lioness has succeeded.
这头非凡的雌狮成功了
王朝 幕后纪实
To follow the story of Charm and her family,
为了追踪查姆和它的家族的故事
the Dynasties team travelled to the Masai Mara,
王朝摄制组来到马赛马拉
one of these big cats' last strongholds.
这些大型猫科动物最后的生存地之一
The crew's aim is to immerse themselves in the lives
摄制组的目的是通过400多天的
of these powerful predators, following them closely
近距离跟踪 潜心记录这些
for over 400 days.
强大的食肉动物的生活
But first, they need to master the tricky task of identifying
不过首先他们需要完成一项棘手的任务
each individual lion.
那就是辨认出每头狮子
Every lion has its own unique set of whisker spots,
每头狮子都有一套独特的胡须点
and put that together with coat colour, ear notches, nose colour,
加上毛色 耳朵切口 鼻子颜色
you can pretty much identify that lion.
完全可以辨认出那头狮子
It would be really great if we could stick moustaches on them and glasses
要是我们能给它们粘上胡须 戴上墨镜和帽子
and hats, because that would make it a lot easier for everybody
那就太好了 因为这样一来 大家就更容易
to understand who they were!
辨认它们是谁了
After weeks of following the family for 12 hours a day,
摄制组每天工作12小时 跟踪家族数周后
they're getting to know the lions.
他们越来越了解狮子
And the lions, it seems, are getting to know them, too.
看起来狮子也越来越了解他们
Well done.
干得好
It was the closest I've ever been.
我第一次和狮子靠这么近
She had her chin over the door. Yeah!
它把下巴伸进了车门
I mean, my feet are within two feet of her.
我的脚离它只有不到60厘米
She's big when she's that close.
那么近的距离 它显得好大
Before long, it becomes clear that each lion
不久之后 大家都清楚了 每头狮子
has its own particular character.
都有自己独一无二的特点
On a long project like this, there's a real luxury,
像这样的长期项目有一大好处
and the luxury is you get to know the individuals.
好处就是你能了解每个个体
They are different to each other.
它们各有不同
Some sit and follow, others watch.
有的坐着跟随 其他观察
Some are into everything, some are funny,
有的对一切都很好奇 有的很可笑
some are really stupid, in a way.
有的还真的有点蠢
I mean, you can see the rest of the pride kind of rolling
你能看到当另一头雄狮加入后 又一次捕猎失手
their eyes as yet another male comes in and blows another hunt.
狮群的其他成员那有点鄙夷的眼神
You begin to care for them.
你开始关心它们
You can't help it.
你忍不住
Charm, she is what a lion should be.
查姆拥有一头狮子应该拥有的一切
She's a provider, she's a mother, she looks after cubs
它供养狮群 它是母亲 它照顾别人的幼崽
that aren't her own, she's the matriarch.
它是女族长
She's the... She's the dame.
它是女王
The crew's attachment to the lions is what makes
摄制组对狮子的感情令接下来的事情
what happens next so hard to deal with.
变得难以接受
Poisoning is one of the biggest threats lions face
中毒是如今非洲的狮子面临的
across Africa today.
最大威胁之一
It can...
如果
It becomes very close to home when it's animals that you know
中毒的是你非常熟悉的动物
so well, individuals.
是我们那么了解的个体
We know them really well now.
我们真的感到了切肤之痛
It's, um, much more...
加倍的痛
Erm, you feel it much more.
感受更加强烈
Soon after the pride leave him, emergency wildlife vets arrive
狮群离去不久之后 紧急野生动物兽医就抵达了
to try and save Charm's youngest son.
试图拯救查姆最小的儿子
But the poison has no simple antidote.
可是没有简单的解毒药
The vets try to ease the symptoms.
兽医试图缓解症状
All they and the crew can do now is wait in the hope he can recover
如今全摄制组只能等待 希望它能康复
and return to the pride.
返回兽群
Eventually, it becomes clear nothing more can be done for him.
最终大家都明白了 对它无能为力
This animal is in a very bad condition, a critical condition,
这头狮子的情况相当糟糕 危在旦夕
and we think it's not going to make it.
我们觉得它凶多吉少
Across Africa, the need for teams like these is on the rise,
在非洲 对这种小组的需求日渐增加
treating wildlife after encounters with man.
在野生动物与人类相遇之后 对它们进行治疗
It's just entirely wrong, isn't it?
这简直大错特错 不是吗
Lions are so endangered.
狮子濒临灭绝
There are hardly any of them, really.
数量稀少
This is one of the best places in the world.
这是全世界最好的地方之一
They're disappearing so quickly, and then this happens to them.
它们消失得非常快 然后发生了这种事
Because of pressure on the land, of people.
因为土地压力 到处都是人
Conflict between humans and lions is increasing
在这片大陆上 人类与狮子之间的冲突
throughout the continent.
与日俱增
Dr Shivani Bhalla is a Kenyan conservationist who has been working
西瓦利巴娜博士是肯尼亚自然资源保护者
with lions and local communities for over a decade.
在过去十多年间 她一直与狮子和当地社区打交道
So many people are surprised to hear that there's only about 20,000 lions
当听到非洲仅存大约两万头狮子 很多人
left in Africa.
都非常惊讶
There's less than 2,000 lions left in Kenya.
在肯尼亚 狮子的数量不足两千头
They are disappearing so quickly.
它们消失的速度相当快
Lions don't have enough food and they don't have enough space,
狮子得不到充足的食物 得不到充足的空间
but communities also don't have enough grazing
同时 社区也缺少足够的草原
for their livestock.
放牧牲畜
They also don't have enough space.
他们也得不到充足的空间
We've got to try and understand both sides of the picture.
我们试图理解双方的情况
Coexistence between people and lions is possible.
人类与狮子共存是可能的
Our strategy has been working with warriors,
我们的策略是 让勇士
women, children, to really bring them on board and engage them
女人 孩子加入到保护狮子的队伍中来
in lion conservation, because they're the ones herding
因为每天放牧的人是他们
livestock every day, they're the ones coming into contact
每天与野生动物接触的人
with wildlife every day.
是他们
Community programmes have shown that lions can actually recover
社区计划表明 在狮子曾经生活
in areas where they used to be once, but then their numbers
后来因为被杀 数量减少的地区
declined because they were being killed.
狮子有复原的力量
And Sophie and John witness that power of recovery
在这里 在查姆身上 索菲和约翰
first-hand, here with Charm.
亲眼见证了恢复的力量
Well, that's that, I think.
就是那里 我觉得
Today's the day.
就是今天
She's gone in there now to have her cubs,
它现在进去产子
which is quite exciting, really.
太令人激动了
We're kind of living it with her, really, aren't we?
我们现在算是和它一起生活了 不是吗
It's about sharing that experience.
关键在于分享这段经历
That's the whole point. That's why we're making the film.
这是重点 也是我们拍摄的原因
Over a year ago, the team set out to find a lion
一年多前 摄制组找到一头狮子
and to tell its story.
讲述它的故事
And here we are, over a year later, and just there,
一年多后 我们来到这里 就在那边
where the camera's pointing, we've got Charm and two little cubs.
摄影机面对的地方 我们拍到了查姆和两头幼崽
She's had such a hard, hard year.
它这一年的日子很不好过
I don't think any of us could've predicted a happier, better way.
我们谁都想不出更快乐更美好的方式
She's the most amazing lion.
它是最神奇的狮子
She's just incredible.
简直不可思议
And... It's the perfect ending, really.
这真是完美的结局
Lions are incredibly resilient.
狮子的适应能力惊人
Given space, enough food and security, they can bounce back.
只要给予空间 足够的食物与安全 它们就能再次崛起
The challenges facing lion conservationists are formidable.
狮子保护区面临严峻的挑战
Indeed, unbelievable though it may sound,
虽然听起来难以置信
there is a real possibility that, before long, lions in the wild
但是在不远的将来 世界上的狮子有可能
could disappear entirely.
彻底消失
But if conservationists and the people who have to live
假如自然资源保护者 以及必须和这些狩猎的大型野兽
alongside these great beasts of prey can work together,
共同生活的人们能携手努力
there is still a chance to save them.
我们依然有机会拯救它们
Next time - one of the last great families of painted wolves.
下集请观看 世上仅存的非洲野犬大家族之一
An intense rivalry.
一场激烈的斗争
Mother against daughter, each striving to rule.
母女反目 各自都想维系统治
Who will triumph, and can they bring peace to these lands?
谁能胜出 并给这片土地带来和平呢？